James M. Hardaway

Cary, NC | (703) 943-8179 | james.m.hardaway@icloud.com | linkedin.com/in/jamesmhardaway

EXECUTIVE SUMMARY

Army Veteran with 27 years of demonstrated performance solving complex problems in information systems integration and intelligence operations management in the United States, Asia, Europe, and the Middle East. Extensive background in Leadership Development, Program Management, Strategic Planning, and Technology Integration. Insightful leader with proven history adapting to and creating change in organizations of 500+ team members. Seeking opportunities in organizational transformation, project management, and technology integration. Career supported by Master of Science in Administration and Leadership. Currently pursuing a Master's Degree in Learning Design and Technology, with a focus on Learning Analytics.

EXPERIENCE

NC STATE UNIVERSITY LABORATORY FOR ANALYTIC SCIENCES

Student Intern, Summer Conference for Applied Data Science, Raleigh, NC (06/2022 – 08/2022)

50-person cohort comprised of the Department of Defense, academia, and industry professionals to ideate, prototype, and experiment on an AI model that autogenerates tailored daily reports for Intelligence Community knowledge workers.

- Organized and edited a 40-page research paper capturing eight weeks of experiments, results, and insights.
- Designed machine learning models capable of automating the summarization of unstructured text documents.
- Developed a knowledge-sharing workflow integrating four separate and distinct data science processes.
- Learned and executed data science processes using Python code in Jupyter Notebook and Visual Studio Code.

UNITED STATES ARMY 09/1994 – 07/2021

Division Chief, Information Systems Requirements Integration, Fort Eustis, VA (08/2019 - 07/2021)

25-person division modernizing Army information systems to provide future warfighters with concepts, capabilities, and organizational structures. Integrated acquisition efforts for an information system portfolio valued at over \$15 billion.

- Guided 12 new programs through acquisition process increasing information and cyber security across the Army.
- Integrated analytic support for two strategic budget assessments, resulting in \$2 billion in cost savings.
- Led design effort to upgrade communications architecture, reducing implementation timeline by two years.
- Chaired virtual synchronization forum connecting participants in five disparate locations, reducing travel costs.

Deputy Director, Intelligence Capabilities Development, Fort Huachuca, AZ (10/2017 - 07/2019)

400-person organization developing modernization solutions for intelligence systems and organizations. Synchronized staff support to subordinate divisions, led new concept development and managed an annual budget of \$36 million.

- Administered the realignment of personnel and equipment to new organizational structure and reporting hierarchy.
- Transformed organizational hiring processes enabling the efficient acquisition of three senior managers.
- One of six selectees for a strategic integration initiative spanning the Army intelligence enterprise.

Division Chief, US and Multinational Intelligence Production, Iraq and Kuwait (08/2016 – 09/2017)

100-person division executing threat analysis to inform strategic decision-making. Guided production of classified analytic products to support senior executive decisions for an organization of 10,000 operating in Iraq and Syria.

- Presented 25 daily briefs to US Ambassador to Iraq informing strategic decisions.
- Prepared and digitally delivered over 50 weekly intelligence updates to senior leaders in multiple locations.
- Published over 100 daily operations summaries to inform the global intelligence enterprise.
- Integrated several new information technology platforms to better aggregate and visualize complex data streams.

Deputy Director, Intelligence Programs, Policy, and Resource Management, Fort Bragg, NC (04/2015 - 07/2016)

150-person organization executing threat analysis to inform strategic decision-making. Provided staff supervision, training, and operations management support while managing an annual budget of \$1 million.

- Performed as both Deputy Director and Operations Manager, balancing short-term requirements with long-term planning and resource management.
- Recruited and integrated 90 new personnel as organization expanded to meet additional global mission requirements.
- Reorganized and trained workforce as it executed a new operational design, excelling during critical evaluation period.

Managing Director/Battalion Commander, Staff Support and Resource Management, Fort Bliss, TX (01/2013 – 03/2015) 900-person organization providing daily operational support to senior executive staff. Supervised training prioritization and resource allocation for a 2-star headquarters while managing a budget of \$2 million.

- Spearheaded the relocation of a 110-person staff to the Kingdom of Jordan within 60 days of notification.
- Established a 75-person training organization to design and teach three Army qualification courses.
- Developed a training management program resulting in 90% of organization achieving fully trained status.
- Partnered with elementary school guiding workforce to volunteer over 200 hours on student enrichment activities.

Deputy Director, Intelligence Programs, Policy, and Resource Management, Fort Belvoir, VA (03/2011-12/2012)

100-person directorate executing cyber threat analysis to inform strategic decision-making. Provided staff supervision, policy, and program management support while managing an annual budget of \$1 million.

- Authored position description and professional requirements for newly established Senior Manager position.
- Expanded organization, recruiting and integrating a team of 10 to analyze human factors in cyberspace.
- Credentialed in cyberspace planning and sensitive information system operations.

Division Chief, Intelligence Analysis, Plans, and Production, Germany and Iraq (07/2008 - 02/2011)

120-person division executing threat analysis to inform strategic decision-making. Guided production of classified analytic products to support senior executive decisions for an organization of 15,000 operating in Germany and Iraq.

- Organized, trained, and deployed 120-person element to Iraq providing intelligence analytic support through various technologies across multiple disparate headquarters.
- Created over 150 digital analytic products supporting operations for a force of 22K U.S and multinational personnel.
- Liaised with multinational partners, training them on information technology (IT) systems and analytic procedures.

Operations Manager and Senior Instructor, Fort Huachuca, AZ (09/2003 – 06/2006)

900-person organization executing entry-level technical training for intelligence analysts and managers. Provided classroom instruction, operations management, and staff training support for a mid-level executive headquarters.

- Revitalized annual training program, incorporating 50 new job tasks while maintaining a unit readiness level consistently above 98%.
- Designed digital learning curriculum and taught multiple courses for junior to mid-tier professionals, graduating over 300 students with professional IT certifications.
- Awarded Knowlton Award for career excellence in Military Intelligence.

EDUCATION AND CERTIFICATIONS

Student, M. Ed., Learning Design & Technology, NC State University, Raleigh, NC – Graduates December 2022 Master of Military Arts and Sciences, US Army Command and General Staff College, Fort Leavenworth, KS – 2008 Master of Science, Administration, Leadership, Central Michigan University, Mount Pleasant, MI – 2007 Bachelor of Science, Civil Engineering, NC State University, Raleigh, NC – 1994

Certificate of Learning Analytics, College of Education, NC State University, Raleigh, NC – 2022

Capability Developer, Defense Acquisition University – 2019

Cyberspace Operations Planner, US Cyber Command – 2014

Basic Computer Network Operations, US Cyber Command – 2011

Strategic Planner, US Army Command and General Staff College – 2008

Joint Planner, US Army Command and General Staff College – 2007

Basic/Intermediate Instructor, US Army Intelligence Center of Excellence – 2004

AWARDS, HONORS, AND PROFESSIONAL ASSOCIATIONS

SALUTE Veterans National Honor Society, 2022 Student Veterans of America, 2021 – Present Military Intelligence Corps Association – National Board Secretary, 2018 – 2019